Guide to the Tanja Lorkovic Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Tanja Lorkovic papers
1940-2013
MS 1627
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
6
18 boxes
104
The papers consist of materials relating to the coup d'état in the Soviet Union and the democracy movement in the Baltic States. The material was gathered by Tanja Lorkovic during the International Federation of Library Associations (IFLA) conference in Moscow in 1991 and during trips to Baltic libraries. Also included are correspondence and related materials pertaining to the Slavic and East European Collection at Yale University Library, the Slavic and East European Section (SEES) of the Association of College and Research Libraries (ARL) of which Lorkovic is a past chairperson, as well as subject files of the Russian library assessment projects organized by her and sponsored by the International Research and Exchanges Board (IREX). Correspondence with literary and political figures is included, as well as an interview with Lorkovic.
Lorković, Tanja
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Tanja Lorkovic, 1992, 1997, 1999, 2001-2003, 2007, 2008, 2010-2011, 2013, and 2014.
Conditions Governing Access
Personnel records (box 2) of Accession 2014-M-037 are restricted as established by Yale Corporation regulations. n.
Original audio, film, and video recordings, as well as preservation masters and duplicating masters may not be played. Readers may only play use copies. If a use copy of a particular recording does not exist, researchers must consult with the reference archivist for policies and procedures regarding the creation of duplicating master and use copies of original recordings.
Original born digital files, as well as preservation masters, may not be accessed due to their fragility. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist request that they be made. Born digital files cannot be accessed remotely. System requirements include a Manuscripts and Archives computer and file viewing software.
Arrangement
The materials are arranged by accession.
Biographical / Historical
Tatjana Bujas Lorkovic was born on January 17, 1933, in Beograd, Yugoslavia. She emigrated to the United States in 1964. She received an M.A. in Yugoslav Languages and Literatures and Russian Language and Literature from the University of Croatia at Zagreb in 1957; an M.A. in Library Science from the University of Minnesota in 1968; and an M.A. in Russian Language and Literature from the University of Iowa in 1972. Lorkovic worked at the University of Iowa as Slavic librarian (1968-1972) and as head of the cataloging department (1973-1989). From 1989 until her retirement in January 2014, she served as curator of the Slavic and East European Collection at Yale University.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of materials relating to the coup d'état in the Soviet Union and the democracy movement in the Baltic States, gathered by Tanja Lorkovic during the International Federation of Library Associations (IFLA) conference in Moscow in 1991 and during trips to Baltic libraries. Also included are correspondence and related materials pertaining to the Slavic and East European Collection at Yale University; the Slavic and East European Section (SEES) of the Association of College and Research Libraries (ARL) of which Lorkovic is a past chairperson, as well as subject files of the Russian library assessment projects organized by her and sponsored by the International Research and Exchanges Board (IREX). Correspondence with literary and political figures is included, as well as an interview with Lorkovic.
Baltic States -- History -- Autonomy and independence movements; Coups d'état -- Soviet Union; International librarianship; Katyn Massacre, Katynʹ, Russia, 1940; Soviet Union -- History -- Attempted coup, 1991; Bujas, Srećko; Ivančan, Dubravko, 1931-; Lorković, Tanja; Novak, Slobodan, 1924-; Association of College and Research Libraries. Slavic and East European Section; International Research and Exchanges Board
- Inventory
  Scope and Contents
  This initial accession to the papers comprises newspaper issues, posters, magazine articles, clippings and other propaganda materials that were circulating among the protesters in Moscow during the August Putsch of 1991 (August 19-22). In the Putsch, a group of members of the Soviet Union's government deposed Mikhail Gorbachev and attempted, with the help of the army, to take control of the country. The coup leaders were hard-line communists who feared that Gorbachev's "Perestroika" reforms went too far, and that the expected new union treaty among the Soviet Republics gave too much power to the republics and weakened the central government. Although the coup collapsed after three days and Gorbachev returned to power, the August Putsch proved to be the beginning of the end of the Soviet Union.
  Lorkovic, in Moscow at the time attending the IFLA (International Federation of Library Associations) conference, was overwhelmed by the events, since the streets of Moscow filled with tanks and everybody was expecting the street fights to start any moment. She took photographs of the street events and collected materials documenting these turbulent and historical days. Some posters were pulled down from the walls at metro stations, some papers purchased from the newspaper stands, and some materials were distributed by protesters with whom Lorkovic mingled in the streets. She was also given photocopied materials by Russian librarian colleagues.
  Lorkovic left Moscow on the 25 August 1991 for the Baltic countries, visiting Tallinn, Tartu, Riga, and Vilnius and witnessing the joy and celebration of peoples who had just obtained their independence after many years of subjugation to the Soviet Union.
  - Photographs
    - Military and civilian action during and after the coup, 1991 August (Box 1, Folder 1 - 3)
    - Václav Havel at the 150th anniversary of the birth of composer Antonin Dvorak in Nelahozeves, Czechoslovakia, 1991 September 8 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Official decrees and proclamations issued during the coup, photocopies, 1991 August (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Report on the IFLA conference in Moscow and visit to Baltic libraries, 1991 August 17-September 17 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Notes, 1991 August (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Printed ephemera, primarily newspapers and leaflets
    - "Yeltsin's Remarks: A Revolutionary Coup," New York Times article, 1991 August 19 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Moskovskii komsomolets: obshchestvenno-politicheskaia molodezhnaia gazeta.
      - 1991 Aug 23 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - 1991 Aug 24 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Golos: obshchestvenno-politicheskii ezhenedel'nik
      - No. 32: 1991 Aug 19-25 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - No. 33: 1991 Aug 26-Sep 1 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - No. 34: 1991 Sep 2-8 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Moskovskie novosti, 1991 August 24 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Moskovskie novosti, an informational leaflet, Ca. 1991 August (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Moscow News: Independent weekly, 1991 August 18-25 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Kommersant: ezhenedel'nik informatsionnoi sluzhby "Fakt"
      - 1991 Aug 19-26 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - 1991 Aug 19-26, photocopy (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Argumenty i fakty: ezhenedel'naia gazeta
      - No. 33: 1991 Aug (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - No. 34: 1991 Aug issue (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Svobodnoe slovo: gazeta moskovskoi organizatsii partii Demokraticheskii soiuz "Grazhdanskii put'": ezhenedel'nik, No. 31, 1991 August 27 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Svoboda i zhizn': nezavisimaia demokraticheskaia gazeta = Freedom & Life
      - No. 7 (spetsvypusk): 1991 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - No. 8: 1991 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - The Baltic Independent: The English-Language Weekly of Estonia, Latvia, Lithuania
      - No. 72: 1991 Aug 16-22 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - No. 72: 1991 Aug 16-22 (an insert with pages 3 and 4 is missing) (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - No. 74: 1991 Aug 30-Sep 5 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Dimitrovgrad panorama: gorodskaia obshchestvenno-politicheskaia gazeta, an informational leaflet with an address to the citizens of Russia, photocopy, 1991 August 20 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Istoki: vsesoiuznaia gazeta, 1991 July (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Slovenske narodne noviny: tyzdennik matice slovenskej, 1991 September 10 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Dvuglavyi orel: rossiiskaia monarkhicheskaia gazeta, No. 1, 1991 January (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Reporter: rossiiskoe obozrenie. No. 3 (pages 5-12 are missing), 1991 February (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Kapital: gazeta dlia bogatykh, 1991 May (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Put': gazeta rossiiskogo khristianskogo demokraticheskogo dvizheniia, No. 6/9, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Levyi bereg: gazeta dlia vzroslykh i detei, 1991 August 12-18 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Megapolis-Continent: mezhdunarodnaia gazeta, 1991 June 26-July 2 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Stranichka uznika: biulleten', No. 13, 1990 June-August (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Sobranie: nezavisimaia gazeta: daidzhest otechestvennoi i zarubezhnoi pressy, No. 8, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - "Materials of Soviet Coup," a catalog of materials for sale, 4 loose sheets (Part 1: "Special issues of newspapers and magazines"; Part 2: "Ukazy, postanovleniya, resheniya, prikazy, obrashceniya"; Part 3: "History, analysis, comments in newspapers and magazines"; Part 4: "Appeals of different political organizations and leaflets") (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - "Documenty obshchestva "Memorial": 10 mikrofish," a catalog (Moscow), 1991 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - "Pamyat': dokumenty i teksty by V. Pribylovski," photocopy of a table of contents (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - "Avtoritet vozhdia: zaiavlenie Natsional'no-Patrioticheskogo Fronta "Pamiat': na semi listakh za deviat'iu podpisiami," pamphlet (pages 3-7 are missing) (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Kongress sootechestvennikov/ (Klip: spetsial'noe prilozhenie), Ca. 1991 August (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Provintsial'naia khronika: rossiiskaia obshchestvenno-politicheskaia gazeta, 1991 April 22 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Vieche: nezavisimoe patrioticheskoe izdanie (Sankt-Peterburg), No. 5, photocopy, 1990 August (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Nezavisimaia gazeta
      - 1991 Aug 21, special issue, photocopy (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - No. 99, 1991 August 24 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - "K grazhdanam Rossii," Yeltsyn's address to the nation, faded original and photocopy, 1991 August 19 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - "Sootechestvenniki!", flyer printed by Konservativnaia partiia, Svobodnoe Mezhprofessional'noe Ob''edinenie Trudiashchikhsia (SMOT), and Komitet Sotsial'noi Zashchity: (Moscow), 1991 May (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Moskovskii bibliotechnyi vestnik
      - No. 3: 1991 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - No. 6: 1991 (spetsial'nyi vypusk) (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Library of Congress Information Bulletin: supplement. Vol.51, containing an IFLA report, 1992 March (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - "IFLA Conference in Moscow," an excerpt from The Cape Librarian: official monthly journal of the Cape Provincial Library Service, 1992 January (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Additional Material, 1971-1996; Accession 1997-M-180
  This accession comprises materials pertaining to the activities of the Slavic and East European Section (SEES) of the Association of College and Research Libraries (ACRL). The papers were compiled by Tanja Lorković, past chair of the SEES and includes correspondence, meeting minutes, agendas, memoranda, printed material, and writings.
  - SEES material
    - 1971-1989 (Box 1, Folder 1 - 10)
    - 1990-1997 and undated (Box 2, Folder 11 - 16)
- Additional Material, 1950-1953; Accession 1999-M-121
  - Correspondence between Tanja Lorkovic and Dubravko Ivancan [Croatian poet], 1950-1953 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, 1990-2001; Accession 2001-M-042
  This accession comprises materials compiled by Tanja Lorkovic as organizer of the library assessment project funded by the Special Projects in Library and Information Science Program of the International Research and Exchanges Board (IREX). The files contain correpondence, project proposals and summaries, printed material, and photographs pertaining to librarianship in Russia after the fall of Communism. The accession also includes printed material and photographs of Eastern European libraries.
  - IREX library and archive assessment projects
    - Kaliningrad (1999), 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 1 - 3)
    - North Caucasus and Volga Basin (1995), 1994-2001 (Box 1, Folder 4 - 6)
    - Ural Region (1999), 1999-2001 (Box 1, Folder 7 - 10)
    - Western Russia (1997) (Box 1, Folder 11 - 15)
  - Photographs of libraries and librarians, and an article, "Revolution Not Over for Eastern European Libraries," by Lorkovic, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Additional Material, 1990-2002; Accession 2001-M-069
  This accession comprises photographs taken by Tanja Lorkovic on various acquisitions trips, depicting various libraries and staff; conferences; exhibits; and political events and politicians of Eastern Europe.
  - Bulgaria, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Croatia [President Franjo Tudjman at Yale University], 1991 September (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Czech Republic and Prague, Circa 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Estonia, 1991 August 26-27 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Hungary and Budapest, 1992 September (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Latvia, 1991 August 28-29 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Lithuania, 1991 August 28-29 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Russia and Moscow, 1990-1994 (Box 1, Folder 8 - 10)
  - Ukraine and Tver, 1998 June (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - United States
    - Dr. Pasko Rakic, Ankica Tudjman, Tanja Lorkovic, Dr. Franjo Tudjman, and Mirjan Damaska at Pierson College, Yale University, 1990 September (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Tanja Lorkovic, unidentified woman, Mirjan Damaska, Stjepan Mesic at Mory's, 2000 September (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Dr. Vladimir Zaitsev and Tanja Lorkovic at the New York Public Library, 2002 October (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Additional Material, 1940; Accession 2002-M-065
  - Report to Stalin, prepared by L. Beria (People's Commissar of International Affairs, USSR), ordering the Katyn Forest Massacre and English translation, photocopy, 1940 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, Accession 2003-M-079
  - Correspondence in Croatian with Slobodan Novak, includes photograph, undated (Box 1)
- Additional Material, 2010; Accession 2011-M-022
  - "The Past as Prologue: Building Yale University Library's Slavic and East European Collection from the Beginning of the Twentieth Century until Today," by Tanja Lorkovic, 2010 (Box 1)
    Includes related correspondence with Gaddis Smith, Larned Professor of History emeritus.
- Additional Material, 1980, 1990-1997, 2010; Accession 2011-M-043
  - Corrrespondence
    Correspondence is both personal and professional. Some letters refer to the Croatian situation in the 1990s.
    - 1980, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1992 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1994-1997, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Interview of Tanja Lorkovic by Robert J. Donia
    The interview with Tanja Lorkovic was conducted on March 29, 2010, by Professor Robert J. Donia, University of Michigan, regarding her uncle Srećko Bujas and his life during World War II and as a judge in Sarajevo, as well as Lorkovic's experiences during the war.
    - Audiorecording, 2010 March 29; 1
    - Transcript, 2010 March 29
      - Digital, 1 (Box 2)
        Conditions Governing Access
        Original born digital files, as well as preservation masters, may not be accessed due to their fragility. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist request that they be made. Born digital files cannot be accessed remotely. System requirements include a Manuscripts and Archives computer and file viewing software.
      - Paper (Box 1, Folder 4)
        The transcript was prepared by Tanja Lorkovic and contains additional information not present on the audiorecording.
- Additional Material, 1977, 1985, 1991-1997; Accession 2012-M-037
  Arrangement
  Files are arranged alphabetically.
  This accession consists primarily of correspondence with Croatian literary and political figures. Aspects of Lorkovic's international librarianship are documented in Topical Files and Writings.
  - Correspondence
    - General, 1993 January, 1995 January (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Grmek, Mirko Dražen, 1993 November 4, 1994 December 8, 1996 January 5 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Novak, Slobodan, 1977 June 14 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Pavletić, Vlatko, 1991 January 18 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Šarić, Artur, 1977 January 9 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Correspondence regarding events in Zagreb.
    - Šoljan, Antun, 1993 May 23 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Stipčević, Aleksandar, 1994 September 17 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - United States Congress. House of Representatives, 1991 December-1992 May 8 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Correspondence regarding Serbian military aggression in Croatia.
  - Topical Files
    - Books for Bosnia project, 1996-1997 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Lorkovic was instrumental in leading a Yale effort to assist in restoring The Bosnia-Herzegovina National Library destroyed by Serb artillery.
    - University of North Sumatra, Indonesia, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Lorkovic was selected as one of four library consultants to participate in the Indonesian Education Project at the University of North Sumatra.
  - Writings
    - "Acquisitions Trip to the Three Baltic States: Estonia, Latvia, and Lithuania, June 3-June 14, 2009," Slavic & East European Information Resources (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Additional Material, 2012-2013; Accession 2013-M-068
  - "The Past as Prologue: Building Yale University Library's Slavic and East European Collection from the Beginning of the Twentieth Century until Today," abridged Russian version in Bibliotekovedenie, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Yale University Library Has Digitized Its Legacy Slavic Collection Created by Joel Sumner Smith," by Tatjana Lorković, Graziano Krätli, and Carolyn Caizzi
    - Published article, Slavic and East European Information Resources, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Abridged Russian translation, Rumiantsevskie chteniia, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Additional Material, 1999, 2003; Accession 2014-M-030
  - Article in Kaliningradskaia Pravda, a Kaliningrad weekly newspaper, 1999 May 27 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    The article features an international seminar attended by Tatjana Lorković, curator of the Slavic and East European Collection at Yale University Library, Michael Neubert, Library of Congress, and archivist Ellen Scaruffi. Topics included the roles of women and the leadership roles held by men in libraries and archives; disparity of pay between men and women, often irregardless of qualifications; the increasing number of men entering the profession, causing a rise in salaries; and the need to recognize the commitment of librarians and archivists to their profession and compensate them accordingly. (page 8)
  - 2003 calendar highlighting the 300th anniversary of St. Petersburg, 2002 December-2003 December (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Additional Material, 1988-2013; Accession 2014-M-037
  The accession comprises primarily correspondence files with individuals, e.g., Yale faculty, domestic and foreign librarians, or on special subjects related to Slavic and Eastern European studies and libraries.
  - Correspondence
    - Africa, 1991- 1997 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Alexandrov, Vladimir, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Asia, 1992-1996 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Banac, Ivo, 1989-1997 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Croatia, 1989-1997, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Hungary, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Library of Congress, 1989-1996 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Les Livres Etrangers, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Lorkovic, Tanja-personal, 1988-1996, 2008-2013 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
    - Montias, Michael, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Poland, 1990-1994 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Richardson, Tom, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Soviet Union, 1990, 1995, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Steinberg, Mark, 1989-1992, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Ukraine, 1992-1995 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - United States, 1989-1996 (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
    - Wandycz, Piotr, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Western Europe, 1989-1997 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Yale related, 1990-2013 (Box 1, Folder 21-22)
  - Bibliographies, research, 1990-1991, 2000-2007 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Photograph of Tanja Lorkovic with Gulissa Kabarovna Balabekova, director of the Kazakh National Library, 2007 October (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Personnel file of Tanja Lorkovic, Undated (Box 2)
    Personnel records are restricted until January 1, 2090 as established by Yale Corporation regulations.
- Additional Material, 1974, 1990-2014; Accession 2015-M-066
  - "Assessing the New Soviet Archival Sources" conference, papers and related materials, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
  - Articles and papers by Tanja Lorkovic, 1990-2011 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1994-2014 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Exhibits
    - "Croatia: Themes, Authors, Books" photographs (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Polonica, 1992 spring (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Gubernatorial Reports of Russian Imperial Governors" advertising flyer, Circa 1995 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Politika, Belgrade, Serbia, article on Slavic collections at Yale, 2012 August 15 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Slavic and East European Section (SEES), Association of College and Research Libraries, "Proposal for the Revision and Updating of the Library of Congress Classification Schedules and Subject Heading List Pertaining to the Soviet Union, Eastern Europe and the Balkan Peninsula," final draft, 1974 November (Box 1, Folder 11)